<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>World War II and the Eastern Front</title>
	<subtitle>Mapping the Eastern Front to showcase the scale of the conflict in the region.</subtitle>
	
	<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/feed/" rel="self"/>
	<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/"/>
	<updated>2022-05-03T20:31:13Z</updated>
	<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/</id>
	<author>
		<name>Jakub Berkowicz</name>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>What is this Project?</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/proposal/"/>
		<updated>1939-09-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/proposal/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;topic&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Topic&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/proposal/#topic&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project will focus on the Eastern Front during World War II, also known as the &amp;quot;Great Patriotic War&amp;quot; by the Russian-speaking world due to their late entry against Germany. This was the bloodiest front of the bloodiest conflict in history, seeing tens of millions of soldiers and civilians die due to combat and other external factors like famine or sickness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides being a massive front in terms of manpower, the size of the Eastern Front is hard to grasp. At around 1000 miles stretching from the Baltic Sea all the way down to the Caucuses, the sheer scale of this front is just as difficult to conceptualize. The size of the front played several key roles during the war, giving the Soviet Union enough space to retreat back to Moscow and slow down the Germans, with the invaders having to stretch out already thing logistical supply lines. Understanding how big the front was is therefore an important part of just learning about World War II.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason mapping has been chosen is to give a visual representation, as names and dates can blend together while seeing something on a map is easier to understand intuitively, In addition, sometimes people just don&#39;t know where certain places are located. They might lack knowledge about the region someone closer to the area already possesses, or even worse incorrectly place the location. Maps help resolve this issue and are a good medium to showcase this topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;audience&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Audience&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/proposal/#audience&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The audience of this website can be generally placed as anyone with a passing interest in history, as the goal is to teach people about the scale of the front rather than going into complex military maneuvers or debate tank armor slopes. What little historical context a person needs to understand the topic should be provided in the website itself, but the more a person knows, the better they can understand the information being presented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately the goal is the broadest audience possible, but should that not be feasible then at least people who have prior knowledge about what the Eastern Front was, even if the specifics are lacking. An average user should be able to access the site, without knowing many cities in Eastern Europe, and come out with a general idea of the state of the Eastern Front at various points in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;structure&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Structure&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/proposal/#structure&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This website can be divided into two separate sections: a longer essay form for information, and the maps themselves. An essay will be provided for each major change in the front such as the start, the furthest extent the Germans pushed, and the furthest the Soviets pushed as well. Should there be more time more snapshots can be included, but those are the big three that need to be there. The essays will include information about general force dispositions and important events that have taken place or will soon take place, such as major battles or political events. It is not meant to be a detailed look at the Eastern Front, instead hilighting certain parts to showcase the trends of each year. Certain details and events will be left out, as entire books can be written on individual years themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The maps themselves will use the Google Maps API from last year as the base layer with GeoJSON being used to create different shapes on top of the maps themselves. The reason I want to use the Google Maps API is because of prior experience, but also because it has modern-day borders already set up. While historical borders might also be an option, the goal is to visualize how far the front had gone, and I feel that this will be easier with modern-day borders to give context. Important battle locations and other events will also be marked on the map.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Map of the Conflict in the Eastern Front</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/maptimeline/"/>
		<updated>1940-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/maptimeline/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-scale-of-the-eastern-front&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Scale of the Eastern Front&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/maptimeline/#the-scale-of-the-eastern-front&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Otherwise known as the Great Patriotic War by the Soviets, the Eastern Front of World War II Would see around 30 million deaths occur, both civilian and military. Some of the bloodies battles of the war took place in this region over a thousand miles apart from the Baltic Sea to the Black Sea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Germany&#39;s decision to invade the USSR and the resulting destruction has been atributed a one of the primary, if not the primary cause, of Germany&#39;s eventual defeat. Having to maintain both attempting to bomb Britain out of the war and fighting a war on a different front the same size as New York City to Orlando stretched German resources to the brink.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>1941</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1941/"/>
		<updated>1941-06-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1941/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-nazis-invade-the-soviet-union&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Nazis Invade The Soviet Union&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1941/#the-nazis-invade-the-soviet-union&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.gethistory.co.uk/sites/default/files/2017-03/Operation-Barbarossa.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;German soldiers on top of a tank in the Soviet Union&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invasion of the Soviet Union by Nazi Germany occurred on June 21st, 1941, breaking the promised neutrality pact signed just two years ago. Whether either side truly believed in the legitimacy of the treaty given their ideological differences is debatably, but the invasion initially stunned Stalin, who would not publically address the nation until July 3rd, 11 days later. While it is a common belief that the invasion caught Stalin completely off guard, he did understand that Hitler would turn East at some point following their non-aggression pact (Shepard, 135). The issue was over how early the attack took place and the position it put Germany in, repeating the mistakes of the First World War with Germany forced into two fronts.  On the battlefield, the initial attacks destroyed the command of the Red Army due to the nature of the invasion, forcing commanders to look back to Moscow for orders. The orders that did arrive were not aware of the scale of the invasion and the conditions of the front but were passed along anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-germans-advance&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Germans Advance&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1941/#the-germans-advance&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Strategically the doctrine the Red Army was working with failed to take advantage of the space they were given, with Stalin ultimately controlling how the army would function in a climate of fear and terror. Rather than utilizing the vast amount of land in the west to consolidate the army, Stalin instead wanted the entire front to be defended, a much more difficult prospect than retreating to a better defensible position (Shepherd, 135). Part of the reason why the doctrine was underdeveloped and so tightly controlled by Stalin was because of the dictator&#39;s own actions during the late 30s, in what is known as the Great Purge. Stalin&#39;s paranoia had reached a level not seen before, and fears of traitors in the military and Communist Party manifested in a purge of the armed forces, leading to some of the best commanders either being forced to resign or executed in show trials (Bergström, 11). Soviet forces could almost certainly have held out better than they did given enough warning and the authority to retreat from the front, but Stalin&#39;s insistence on defending the whole front prevented this from occurring. Even basic mobilization was prevented, allowing German planes to destroy 1,200 Soviet aircraft that were lined up outside their airbases within hours of the war starting (Overy, 76). The Germans had the advantage of both strategic surprise and tactical surprise, allowing them to advance rapidly towards Moscow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;German doctrine had been adapted to taking down the USSR following the Invasion of France, further surprising the Red Army. Rather than the smaller engagements followed by a clash between the two armies taking place, the German Army advanced all at once and overwhelmed the defenders, giving them the momentum needed to push forward (Overy, 76). This was consistent with the German utilization of &lt;em&gt;blitzkrieg&lt;/em&gt;, lighting war, which utilized quick pushes supported by air power to quickly encircle their opponents. The German Air Force was so successful in this endeavor that initial flights over the USSR were not met by anti-air defenses or enemy planes, allowing them to reach the massive kill count mentioned earlier (Bergström, 14). The ground war was no different, as the three main Army Groups: North, Center, and South, began their advance East, quickly leading to massive encirclements. One of the first of these pockets was the Minsk Pocket which ended on July 8th following its destruction by Army Group Center. The pocket, which could have possibly gone so far as Smolensk had Hitler not ordered the army to slow down, ended up with 324,000 Red Army troops captured (Shepherd, 137). For comparison, this was double the amount of casualties (Wounded and killed) that Germany suffered from the Invasion of France. This would be the first in a series of pockets across the front as the German Army continued to advance East.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-red-army-holds&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Red Army Holds?&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1941/#the-red-army-holds&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial few months of the war looked like Germany would crush the Soviet Union, as the Red Army failed to mount any real defense until later in the year. With the benefit of hindsight, it is easy to point out that the invasion was a mistake and that Hitler had doomed himself by attacking the USSR. The reality is more complicated, as several factors influenced this decision and made it reasonable in Hitler&#39;s eyes to invade. One critical reason was the issue of resources, as fueling the German war machine required massive imports of vital materials such as oil from other nations. The naval blockade of Germany instituted by Great Britain meant that Germany was forced to rely on the USSR for these resources, paying for these purchases with machine tools and military equipment (Ellman, 80). Following the division of Poland, Red Army troops had to be redeployed to the annexed nation, abandoning their fortifications deeper with the USSR, moving them out of position. The Red Army itself was undergoing massive reforms after the disappointing performance that took place during the Winter War against Finland, and German observers understood that should these reforms pass that the Red Army would become a formidable opponent should they invade (Ellman, 79). Striking at the USSR now would maximize Germany&#39;s chances of victory, as the Red Army embarrassed itself on the world stage against Finland and helped lead Hitler to the conclusion that the Red Army was weak (Ellman, 88-89).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the invasion may have been a success in the initial months, it did not come without a serious cost to the German Army. Most German commanders understood that the Eastern Front had damaged the army, suffering 686,000 casualties by November (20% of the original force and every replacement since June 22), and required a large commitment of forces to continue with 2.7 million men being fielded (Glantz, 181O). Logistically the Germans were overstretched as their rapid advance had to wait for supplies such as fuel to continue their attack, giving the Soviets time to regroup. If Germany wished to win its fight against the USSR, it would have to do it by the time winter started. The advance on Moscow began in earnest on November 15th, with a force of around 233,000 in the main army with a further 240,000 supporting from the north (Glantz, 189O). German troops would continue to advance, at great cost, towards Moscow, but the Red Army had begun to organize more efficiently and mount a defense of the city. Other fronts also began to appear more favorable for the Soviets as the weather helped slow down the advancing Germans. By December 4th the Red Army had prevented the capture of Leningrad and Rostov, along with keeping the Germans from the Caucus region. The German Army was halted on the outskirts of Moscow, and whether the Germans could win became a genuine question. These actions came at the cost of millions of Soviet soldiers, as the war reached a level of brutality not seen on the Western Front. 2.8 million Soviet soldiers would be lost in the first three months, and another 2 million as well by December 31st, virtually wiping out the peacetime reserve of the Red Army (Glantz, 201O).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>1942</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1942/"/>
		<updated>1942-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1942/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;turning-back-the-tide&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Turning Back the Tide&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1942/#turning-back-the-tide&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://images.immediate.co.uk/production/volatile/sites/7/2021/12/AKG185619sml-8b1e414.png?quality=90&amp;amp;webp=true&amp;amp;resize=1000,667&quot; alt=&quot;Soviet soldiers advancing in 1942&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The failure of the German Army to take Moscow by the end of 1941 would start the slow downfall of Germany. Some campaigns during this year managed to push back against the Red Army and seize even more territory such as in the Caucuses, but this inability to seize the capital of the USSR combined with ongoing logistical issues stretched the Germans to their breaking point. The attack on Pearl Harbor by the Japanese and the subsequent declaration of war on America by Germany at the end of 1941 also had massive implications on the Eastern Front despite the inability of the Allies to directly assist the Soviets militarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1942 would be a major year on the Eastern Front, as both sides attempted to stabilize the gains they had achieved and attempt to push back against the opposing side. The Winter Offensive continued from the previous year for the Soviets, while Hitler attempted to find other fronts to press his advantage and secure other objectives instead of Moscow. The ultimate display of brutality and the most significant battle of the year would take place in Stalingrad, leading to the bloodiest battle of the war and a testament to the scale and brutality of the conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-winter-offensive&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Winter Offensive&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1942/#the-winter-offensive&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start of the Winter Offensive took place in December of 1941 and would continue well into 1942. This period marked the furthest the German Army would advance towards Moscow before being pushed back by Zhukov and his counterattack. Coordinating with the rest of the &lt;em&gt;Stavka&lt;/em&gt;, the Soviet high command, Zhukov was able to redeploy 18 divisions and 1700 tanks from Siberia to reinforce his counterattack (Baker, 54). These troops were able to be redeployed due to Japan shifting its focus south rather than assisting in an attack on the USSR due to American economic pressure, forcing the Japanese to strike at Indochina to secure resources like oil and rubber (Ellman, 186). The USSR learned of this decision to go south through Richard Sorge, a spy based in Japan, and allowed the USSR to weaken their Western flank in order to prevent a German victory, significantly swinging the tide of battle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, the Red Army was successful in pushing back the Germans, but Zhukov would become frustrated at the slow progress and the time given for counter maneuvers. On December 9th he issued an order that forced commanders to penetrate enemy formations instead of simply engaging screening forces, helping to lead to possible encirclements appearing over the next few days (Glantz, 214). This advance would continue until 1942 when the Red Army would itself go on the offensive. January 7th saw Stalin issue a general offensive across the front, with the goal of stretching out the German Army which now had to contend with Lend Lease support from the US (Baker, 55). This focus on attrition was crucial, as the &lt;em&gt;blitzkrieg&lt;/em&gt; had relied upon quick victories through its use of mechanized warfare. With resources dwindling, the offensive could not be sustained and the larger size of the USSR could be utilized. Manpower was also an issue, as by the end of 1941 the Germans were losing around 3,000 men a day, a casualty rate that could not be sustained for any length of time (Baker, 56). By March 31st the German advance had been stalled across the front and the Red Army had regained control over conquered parts of the USSR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;summer-1942-fall-blau&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Summer 1942: Fall Blau&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1942/#summer-1942-fall-blau&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The offensive that started in January had forced the Germans to retreat back from the east, but the spring would give them a chance to go on the offensive themselves once again. Rather than focus on the north or central Russia, Hitler&#39;s focus would be on the south towards the Caucasus region of the USSR. Codenamed &lt;em&gt;Fall Blau&lt;/em&gt; (Operation Blue), this decision to invade the south hinged on several key factors, notably the economic situation of Germany. The success of the Japanese in the Far East and Erwin Rommel in North Africa gave Hitler the idea that he could link up to these forces through the Middle East and assault the USSR with a combined front, focusing their efforts on knocking out the nation (Overy, 157). Economically the issues with &lt;em&gt;blitzkrieg&lt;/em&gt; begin to emerge, with the Caucus region being one of the most important oil fields in the USSR. So vital was capturing the petroleum industry that Hitler stated that &amp;quot;If I don&#39;t get the oil of Maikop and Grozny (Two cities in the region), then I Must end the war&amp;quot; (Shepherd, 243). Strategically the choice to focus on the south also allowed Hitler to regain the initiative, surprising the Soviets with a sudden attack. The USSR was prepared for more fighting outside of Moscow given its political importance and its role as the center of communication for the army, a belief that did make sense (Baker, 57). Ultimately Hitler did not follow this line of action, committing himself in a different direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial assault by the Germans was a success, catching the overextended Soviet forces by surprise and taking advantage of the Red Army&#39;s failure to stop the offensive. June 28th saw the start of this plan take place and by July 23rd Rostov-on-Don had been captured by the German Army (Overy, 158). This initial success was devasting for the Soviets, both strategically and for the morale of the public, but due to Hitler&#39;s direct intervention in the planning the seeds of a Soviet victory were planted. The goal of the operation was two-fold: capture the oil fields of the Caucus and take Stalingrad, with both objectives having an army group attached to accomplish this. Rather than allowing Group A to seize the oil fields first, Hitler split his two groups and attempted to take both Stalingrad and the Caucus at the same time (Baker, 63). Initial success for the Germans occurred, but the push south did not go as fast as Hitler would have wanted while at the same time forcing Moscow to react due to the strategic importance of the region. It was during this period that Stalin&#39;s famous Order 227 was delivered, calling for &amp;quot;Not one step back!&amp;quot; and preventing panic retreats among divisions through the use of blocking divisions that would fire upon &amp;quot;cowards and traitors&amp;quot; (Order 227). As the German Army continued to advance, it would stall on August 28th, failing to reach its goal of taking Grozny and showcasing the failure of the operation to the German high command (Baker, 64).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;stalingrad-hell-on-earth&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Stalingrad: Hell on Earth&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1942/#stalingrad-hell-on-earth&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Battle of Stalingrad would begin on August 23rd and last until the following year, ending on February 2nd, 1943. These five months would see some of the most brutal fighting in the European theater, a vignette of the brutality across the front. The Soviet Union was prepared for a battle to take place in the city, with huge reserves being prepared around the northern and southern parts of Stalingrad, and several operation plans were drawn up to encircle and destroy German armies in the region (Baker, 65).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Army tactics in the city were also changed by the commanding general, Vasili Chuikov, to reflect the reality of urban conflict. Losing Stalingrad was not an option, so rather than focus on larger, strategic goals, Chuikov instead dedicated time to tactics that would make the German advance halt and wither away (Overy, 174). Some of these tactics included &amp;quot;hugging&amp;quot; German infantry positions with his own forces, placing them at risk due to their closeness but also preventing effective usage of German artillery and air support over fears of friendly fire (Shepherd, 258). Night attacks were also common, as Soviet troops snuck behind enemy lines to attack isolated German units, and snipers kept overwatch over the streets through all hours of the day (Overy, 175). German units were unable to rest, being forced to lie awake in fear of an attack, sapping both their energy and morale. Smart urban combat was utilized as well, focusing on securing key buildings rather than holding everything in sight, instead of dedicating time to preparing traps and firing fields for troops within (Shepherd, 258). This allowed the Red Army to concentrate its efforts on smaller goals that would give them the defensive advantage against advancing German troops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stalingrad&#39;s fame would be bolstered by the actions that took place in November, as the Red Army began to push back against the German advance yet again. Operation Uranus was the codename for an attack that took place between November 19th and 23rd, leading to the encirclement of Axis forces around Stalingrad, notably the German Sixth Army. This led to 330,000 German soldiers trapped within the city, as they were forced to defend themselves from all sides (Baker, 65). Attempts were made by the Germans to break through from within and attempt to rescue soldiers from outside, but none would succeed. Compounding this was Hitler&#39;s order that refused to allow troops within to retreat from the city, forcing them to fight to the death or their eventual capture (Baker, 67). Ultimately 300,000 German soldiers would be captured or killed by February 2nd, with a further 655,000 coming from allied armies (Shepherd, 271). This victory was won at great cost by the Soviets, however, as significant resources had to be poured into securing the city, and fighting across the front continued as well. By the end of 1942, Soviet casualties were over 11 million, but they had stopped &lt;em&gt;Fall Blau&lt;/em&gt; and the southern push.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>1943</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1943/"/>
		<updated>1943-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1943/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;germany-on-the-defensive&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Germany on the Defensive&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1943/#germany-on-the-defensive&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.militarytimes.com/resizer/r3AukW1UzBCdurTp03CkCYxnqkA=/1440x0/filters:format(png):quality(70)/arc-anglerfish-arc2-prod-mco.s3.amazonaws.com/public/D6O5TOB5S5C3JN3TFQH2VNWKXE.png&quot; alt=&quot;Soviet artillery battery in the Northern Caucasus, 1943&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1943 on the Eastern Front is not often discussed when studying World War II as a whole, being overshadowed by events in North Africa and Italy with US intervention in those regions. With the exception of the Battle of Kursk, no major engagements reached the scale of previous battles that occurred on the front. Despite this, this period was vital in ensuring that Germany would never be able to retake the East, forcing them on the defensive until the Red Army would arrive at the gates of Berlin and fly the hammer and sickle over the Reichstag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The image of the German Army as an unstoppable force that had been able to accomplish unimaginable feats had been smashed following Stalingrad, as news of the failure spread throughout Germany. The same military that had defeated France in six weeks, succeeding where Imperial Germany had failed, was now demoralized with one officer reporting that &amp;quot;I understand nothing anymore. Stalingrad is madness. (Shepherd, 318). The Soviets on the other hand had turned the battle into a legend, showcasing the might of the Red Army standing up against the fascist invaders. To have been present at the battle and survive became a status symbol, and trains moving soldiers once filled with trepidation and fear turned to hope and resistance (Overy, 186). While not the most significant battle of the war, it restored morale to the Soviets and gave them the ability to start their advances in 1944.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-battle-of-kursk&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Battle of Kursk&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1943/#the-battle-of-kursk&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While Stalingrad may have been a significant moral victory for the Soviets, the Battle of Kursk would mark the turning point of the Eastern Front. Following the failure of the German offensive, Germany would never again mount any large-scale strategic attacks on the Eastern Front, as pressure from the West forced them to divert resources to protect Italy. Kursk would also become known as the largest tank battle in history due to the sheer amount of men and equipment committed to the operation from both sides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hitler and his generals understood that they had to strike against the Soviets while their industry was not yet fully recovered following the destruction caused by the last two years. Already in 1943, the USSR was producing 24,000 tanks and 48,000 heavy guns compared to Germany&#39;s 17,000 and 27,000 respectively (Shepherd, 328-329). Operation Citadel, the overall plan that included the Battle of Kursk, can be viewed as a defensive plan, with the goal being to crush a large number of Soviet forces and allow Germany time to recuperate from its losses. The goal of the plan was to encircle the Kursk salient, a protruding area in the German lines by the Red Army, originally being planned for May 3rd (Baker, 73). However, the operation was postponed multiple times due to unfavorable weather conditions, giving the Soviets time to respond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Red Army command was well aware of the appeal that a salient had for the German Army, being a strategically important area to secure. Defensive preparations were made across the front and special attention was paid to Kursk during the four-month lull in fighting on the front. Within the bulge, seven armies were crammed in order to fortify the region and prepare for a potential counterattack. By the start of the battle, over 1.3 million men, 3,444 tanks, 2.900 aircraft, and 19,000 heavy guns were located in the salient on the Soviet side, amounting to 40% of its manpower and 75% of its armored units (Overy, 201). The Germans meanwhile had 900,000 soldiers, 2,700 tanks, 2,000 aircraft, and over 10,000 guns (Overy, 201).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The battle began on Jul 5th with the Germans advancing into the well-prepared Soviet position. Assaults came from the north and south in an attempt to close off the salient, but German troops could not even penetrate the front lines of the Soviet army. Fighting would escalate and reach its peak on July 12th with the massive armored clash at Pokhorovka, and the following day the operation would be canceled by Hitler (Shepherd, 332). Despite the cancellation of Citadel, the Germans were able to achieve some success in terms of material losses against the Soviets. Losing only 1,100 tanks on the German side was somewhat problematic but given both tank production being scaled up and inflicting more losses on the Soviet side, some success was found (Shepherd, 332). The Germans however did fail in their goal of stopping the Soviet advance, not being able to find time to recover. On the Soviet side, the casualties were much lower than what was seen at Stalingrad and other previous battles. 470,000 soldiers were killed in 1942, but Kursk saw only 70,000 casualties across all branches of the Soviet military, and a further 183,000 were lost breaking the German line (Overy, 212). While lower than previous battles, this number is still nearly as many soldiers lost for Britain or the US across the entire war, while the USSR suffered this in only two months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;advancing-west&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Advancing West&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1943/#advancing-west&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the Battle of Kursk, the Soviet Union would continue its advance and reclaim territory it once held from German control. While no event occurred during the Fall and Winter periods that can be considered as significant as Kursk, the offensives that followed the battle helped secure future Red Army success as the German Army was stretched to its limit with new developments in Greece and Italy. In response to the changing nature of the war, Hitler instituted what was known as the &amp;quot;Fortress Europe&amp;quot; policy, with several &amp;quot;walls&amp;quot; being created to protect Germany from further attacks such as the Atlantic Wall or more relevantly the Eastern Wall (&lt;em&gt;Ostwall&lt;/em&gt;) (Shepherd, 357). Positions were taken up at strategically useful locations that could be used to defend against any further Red Army advances, one of these being the Dnieper River. Ukraine would be contested during the fall of 1944, both due to the region&#39;s importance and status as the &amp;quot;breadbasket of Europe&amp;quot;, but also due to the momentum the Red Army had following Kursk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The German formations on the Dnieper were part of a larger series of defenses stretching all the way to Finland, with this particular section being known as the &amp;quot;Wotan Line.&amp;quot; Army Group Center and South were given permission by Hitler to retreat back to this position in order to avoid encirclement and recover across the river, but the Red Army continued to advance. The river itself was an important barrier, with some banks on the east rising up 100 feet and the river itself being 1000 yards wide at some points (Baker, 83). The importance of this river was known to all, and plans were made to get around such a massive roadblock. A combination of the German Army being unable to prepare in time and the use of airborne troops would see the advance continue in the south. The &amp;quot;Wotan Line&amp;quot; had been declared but never properly reinforced and the one advantage this position held was forcing the Red Army to cross a river (Baker, 83). A massive airborne assault was utilized by the Soviets on 23-26 September in order to divert resources away from the line, and despite difficulties was able to allow other elements of the Red Army to succeed in this task a month later. November 3rd saw the Dnieper breached by Soviet forces, and Kyiv fell 3 days later (Baker, 84). The Southern Front was now firmly in control of the Soviets, and further preparations were being made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this success, other parts of the front were somewhat stabilized by the German Army. Army Group North and Center were able to hold out against the onslaught, and forces retreating from the south were able to create new lines that would hold until the following year (Shepherd, 370). However, this did tie up German resources and wear down the army, constantly overstretching the military and allowing other fronts to open up like in Italy.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>1944</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1944/"/>
		<updated>1944-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1944/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-german-army-on-the-defensive&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The German Army on the Defensive&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1944/#the-german-army-on-the-defensive&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By 1944 the Red Army and the Soviet Union had come online and were significantly more prepared to fight materially and in terms of morale. Materially, the 3.1 million Axis soldiers supported by 3,000 aircraft and 2,3000 tanks were not in a position to face off against the 6.4 million Red Army soldiers, the 13,400 planes covering them, and the 5,800 tanks leading them (Overy, 236). The majority of Axis forces were sent to the Eastern Front, and even then the disparity in numbers is staggering. 1944 also saw the Allies embark on D-Day, further reducing the resources available to be sent to the East and exacerbating the situation. Morale among the Red Army was also at an all-time high, no longer on the defensive against the veterans of the German Army they faced in 1941.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limited action would take place during the spring of 1944 due to weather issues, a common theme on the Eastern Front given the importance of mechanized warfare. With the exception of the Liberation of Leningrad, large-scale campaigns could not take place with the mud caused by spring thaws and the rain that followed, forcing both sides to wait out the weather or risk attacks in less than ideal conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;belarus-and-operation-bagration&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Belarus and Operation Bagration&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1944/#belarus-and-operation-bagration&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;liberating-central-europe&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Liberating&amp;quot; Central Europe&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1944/#liberating-central-europe&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>1945</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1945/"/>
		<updated>1945-01-01T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1945/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-eagle-is-slain&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Eagle is Slain&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1945/#the-eagle-is-slain&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;poland-and-reaching-the-german-border&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Poland and Reaching the German Border&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1945/#poland-and-reaching-the-german-border&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-battle-of-berlin&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;The Battle of Berlin&lt;a class=&quot;tdbc-anchor&quot; href=&quot;https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/1945/#the-battle-of-berlin&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;🔗&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Bibliography</title>
		<link href="https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/bibliography/"/>
		<updated>2022-05-03T20:31:13Z</updated>
		<id>https://hackinghistory.github.io/hh-project-11ty-starter-kit/bibliography/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bergström, Christer. Barbarossa: The Air Battle July-December 1941. Hersham, Surrey: Midland, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Glantz, David. Operation Barbarossa: Hitler’s Invasion of Russia 1941. Stroud, Gloucestershire: The History Press, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overy, Richard. Russia’s War. New York: Penguin Books, 1998.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shepherd, Ben H. Hitler’s Soldiers: The German Army in the Third Reich. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>